Baobao Zhang

CONTACT bzhang22@syr.edu http://baobaofzhang.github.io/ INFORMATION Twitter: baobaofzhang Google Scholar: yqpOQRsAAAAJ&hl

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research uses quantitative methods to study how citizens and technical experts could shape the governance of emerging technologies. I have established three main research streams: 1) the politics of digital technologies, with a focus on the governance of artificial intelligence; 2) international political economy in the age of advanced automation; and 3) quantitative social science methods.

ACADEMIC APPOINTMENTS **Syracuse University**: Assistant Professor, Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs, Department of Political Science, 2021–

Core faculty member, Autonomous Systems Policy Institute; Senior research associate, Campbell Public Affairs Institute

Centre for the Governance of AI: Research Affiliate, 2021–

Cornell University: Klarman Postdoctoral Fellow (Cornell Society of Fellows), primary affiliation: Department of Government; secondary affiliation: Department of Information Science, 2020–2021, 2022-2023

University of Oxford: Research Affiliate, Centre for the Governance of AI, University of Oxford, 2018–2021

Harvard University: Fellow 2019–2020; Affiliate 2020–2021, Berkman Klein Center for Internet & Society

Massachusetts Institute of Technology: Postdoctoral Fellow, Department of Political Science, 2019–2020

EDUCATION

Yale University: Ph.D., Political Science, 2020; M.A., Statistics, 2015 Exchange Scholar: Department of Political Science, Massachusetts Institute of Technology (2018–2019; 2015–2016); Nuffield College, University of Oxford (2017–2018)

Yale University: B.A., Political Science, 2013 (with Distinction)

EDITED VOLUME

Oxford Handbook of AI Governance. (Editors: Justin Bullock, Yu-Che Chen, Johannes Himmelreich, Valerie Hudson, Anton Korinek, Matthew Young, and **Baobao Zhang**), forthcoming, Oxford University Press.

PEER-REVIEWED
PUBLICATIONS

1. "Ethics and Governance of Artificial Intelligence: Evidence from a Survey of Machine Learning Researchers." (Baobao Zhang, Markus Anderljung, Lauren Kahn, Noemi Dreksler, Michael C. Horowitz, Allan Dafoe), 2021, *Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research*, 71: 591–666.

DOI: 10.1613/jair.1.12895

2. "COVID-19 Vaccine Acceptance and Hesitancy in Low and Middle Income Countries, and Implications for Messaging." (Julio S. Solís Arce,...,Baobao

Zhang, ..., Ahmed Mushfiq Mobarak), 2021, *Nature Medicine*. DOI: 10.1038/s41591-021-01454-y

- 3. "Skilled and Mobile: Survey Evidence of Immigration Preferences of AI Researchers." (Remco Zwetsloot, **Baobao Zhang**, Noemi Dreksler, Lauren Kahn, Markus Anderljung, Allan Dafoe, and Michael C. Horowitz), 2021, the *Proceedings of the 2021 AAAI/ACM Conference on AI, Ethics, and Society*. DOI: 10.1145/3461702.3462617
- "Americans' Perceptions of Privacy and Surveillance in the COVID-19 Pandemic" (Baobao Zhang, Sarah Kreps, Nina McMurry, and R. Miles McCain), 2020, *PLoS ONE* 15(12): e0242652. Coverage in *Bloomberg* and *IEEE Spectrum*; shared with the World Health Organization.
 DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0242652
- "Factors Associated with US Adults' Likelihood of Accepting COVID-19 Vaccination: Evidence from a Choice-Based Conjoint Analysis" (Sarah Kreps, Sandip Prasad, ..., Baobao Zhang, Douglas L. Kriner), 2020, *JAMA Network Open*, 3(10):e2025594. Coverage by *USA Today* and *Vox*.
 DOI: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.25594
- 6. "Scientists' Political Behaviors Are Not Driven by Individual-level Government Benefits." (Baobao Zhang and Matto Mildenberger), 2020, *PLoS ONE*, 15(5):e0230961.

DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0230961

7. "U.S. Public Opinion on the Governance of Artificial Intelligence." (Baobao Zhang and Allan Dafoe), 2020, the *Proceedings of the 2020 AAAI/ACM Conference on AI, Ethics, and Society.*

DOI: 10.1145/3375627.3375827

- 8. "Coercion and Provocation." (Allan Dafoe, Sophia Hatz, and **Baobao Zhang**), forthcoming at the *Journal of Conflict Resolution*.

 DOI: 10.1177/0022002720957078
- "Quota Sampling Using Facebook Advertisements." (Baobao Zhang, Matto Mildenberger, Peter D. Howe, Jennifer Marlon, Seth Rosenthal, and Anthony Leiserowitz), 2020, Political Science Research and Methods, 8(3), 558–564. doi:10.1017/psrm.2018.49.
 DOI: 10.1017/psrm.2018.49
- "Experimental Effects of Climate Messages Vary Geographically." (Baobao Zhang, Sander van der Linden, Matto Mildenberger, Peter D. Howe, Jennifer Marlon, and Anthony Leiserowitz), 2018, Nature Climate Change, 8:370–374. DOI: 10.1038/s41558-018-0122-0
- 11. "Information Equivalence in Survey Experiments." (Allan Dafoe, **Baobao Zhang**, and Devin Caughey), 2018, *Political Analysis*, 26(4):399–416. DOI: 10.1017/pan.2018.9
- 12. "Viewpoint: When Will AI Exceed Human Performance? Evidence from AI Experts." (Katja Grace, John Salvatier, Allan Dafoe, **Baobao Zhang**, and Owain Evans), 2018, *Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research*, 62: 729-754. No. 16 on Altmetric's top 100 most-discussed articles of 2017. DOI: 10.1613/jair.1.11222

 "Results of a Nationwide Capacity Survey of 94 Hospitals Providing Trauma Care in War-affected Syria, April 2015." (with Hani Mowafi et al.), 2016, *JAMA Surgery*, 151(9):815-822. Coverage by *Reuters*.
 DOI: 10.1001/jamasurg.2016.1297

CHAPTERS IN EDITED BOOK

"Public Opinion Toward Artificial Intelligence." (Baobao Zhang), forthcoming, in the *Oxford Handbook of AI Governance*.
 DOI: 10.31219/osf.io/284sm

WORKS IN PROGRESS

- 1. "No Rage Against the Machines: Threat of Automation Does Not Change Policy Preferences." (Baobao Zhang).
- 2. "Analysis of 193,618 Trauma Patient Presentations in War-affected Syria." (Hani Mowafi, Mahmoud Hariri, **Baobao Zhang**, ..., Anas Al-Kassem).

TECHNICAL REPORTS & POLICY WRITING

- 1. "Building Robust and Ethical Vaccination Verification Systems." (Baobao Zhang, Laurin Weissinger, Johannes Himmelreich, Nina McMurry, Tiffany Li, Naomi Schinerman, and Sarah Kreps), 2021, Brookings Institution.
- "The Immigration Preferences of Top AI Researchers: New Survey Evidence."
 (Remco Zwetsloot, Baobao Zhang, Markus Anderljung, Michael C. Horowitz, and Allan Dafoe), 2021, Perry World House. Cited in the UK National AI Strategy.
- 3. "Contact-tracing Apps Face Serious Adoption Obstacles." (Sarah Kreps, **Baobao Zhang**, and Nina McMurry), 2020, Brookings Institution. Cited by the U.S. Senate.
- 4. "In Defense of Pollsters." (Baobao Zhang), 2020, Fortune.
- 5. "Contact-tracing Apps Face Serious Adoption Obstacles." (Sarah Kreps, **Baobao Zhang**, and Nina McMurry), 2020, Brookings Institution. Cited by the U.S. Senate.
- 6. "Americans Don't Trust Contact Tracing Apps. Here's How We Can Fix That." (Sarah Kreps, Nina McMurry, and **Baobao Zhang**), 2020, *Fortune*.
- 7. "Contribution to a European Agenda for AI." (Adrien Abecassis, Justin B. Bullock, Johannes Himmelreich, Valerie M. Hudson, Jack Loveridge, and **Baobao Zhang**), 2020, Berkman Center for Internet & Society.
- 8. "Artificial Intelligence: American Attitudes and Trends." (**Baobao Zhang** and Allan Dafoe), 2019, Centre for the Governance of AI, Future of Humanity Institute, University of Oxford. Coverage by *Vox*, *MIT Technology Review*, and *Bloomberg News*.
- 9. "Public Opinion Lessons for AI Regulation." (Baobao Zhang), 2019, Brookings Institution.
- 10. "It's 2043. We Need a New American Dream for the A.I. Revolution," (**Baobao Zhang**), August 12, 2019, *New York Times*.
- 11. "Challenges to Democracy at Home and Abroad." (**Baobao Zhang**), 2019, Kerry Initiative, Jackson Institute for Global Affairs, Yale University.

WORKING PAPERS

- "No Rage Against the Machines: Threat of Automation Does Not Change Policy Preferences." Coverage by *Axios*.
- "Hands Off My Medicare?: Self-Interest and Conditional Policy Feedback."

SELECT AWARDS, FELLOWSHIPS, AND GRANTS

CIFAR-Jacobs Foundation Seed Grant (2021), with Kou Murayama, Catherine Lebel, Julia Moeller, Drew Bailey, and Adeel Razi: CA\$50,000

CIFAR Azrieli Global Scholar in the Innovation, Equity & the Future of Prosperity Program (2021): CA\$100,000

Syracuse University Appleby-Mosher Grant (2021): \$1,300

Syracuse University Autonomous Systems Policy Institute Curricular Initiative Grant (2021): \$2,500

Social Science Research Council Just Tech Covid-19 Rapid-Response Grant (2020), with Sarah Kreps, Nina McMurry, and Laurin Weissinger: \$9,000

Berkeley Existential Risk Initiative Grant (2020), with Sarah Kreps: \$10,000

OECD Future of Work Fellowship (2020): €5,000

Russell Sage Foundation Behavioral Economics Grant (2019), with David Knight: \$7,500

Ethics and Governance of AI Fund Grant (2018), with Allan Dafoe: \$250,000 Kerry Fellowship, Yale Jackson Institute for Global Affairs (2018–2019): \$3,000 National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship (2014–2017): \$132,000 in tuition scholarship and stipend

Yale Institution for Social and Policy Studies Field Experiment Grant (2016): \$5,000 Falk Fellowship for the Study of American Politics, Yale University (2013–2014) James Gordon Bennett Prize for Best International Relations Senior Thesis, Yale University (2013)

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Governance and Ethics of Artificial Intelligence, Syracuse University (Fall 2021)

Instructor of record: Baobao Zhang

Introduction to American Politics, Yale University (Summer 2018)

Instructor of record: Baobao Zhang

Politics of Public Policy, Yale University (Spring 2017)

Instructor of record: Jacob Hacker

Advanced Quantitative Methods, Yale University (Fall 2016)

Instructor of record: Allan Dafoe

SELECT PRESENTATIONS & SPEAKING ENGAGEMENTS

- "Public Opinion Toward Artificial Intelligence": CIFAR, 2021 (Invited)
- "NLP for Positive Impact": Joint Conference of the 59th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics and the 11th International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing, 2021 (Invited panelist)
- "Ethics and Governance of Artificial Intelligence: Evidence from a Survey of Machine Learning Researchers": Future of Privacy Forum, 2021 (Invited); Information Society Project, Yale Law School, 2021 (Invited)
- "The Opportunities Challenges of COVID-19 Tracking Apps as Pandemic Control Mechanisms": University of Wisconsin–Madison, 2021 (Invited panelist)

- "Policy, Politics and Ethics of the Coming AI Revolution": Cornell University, 2021 (Invited panelist)
- "Forecasting Process in AI Development: Evidence from Machine Learning Researchers": OECD Future of Work Initiative, 2020 (Invited)
- "Lessons of History, Law, and Public Opinion for AI Development": Brookings Institution, 2019 (Invited)
- "Anxiety of Automation and Policy Preferences": Midwest Political Science Association Conference, 2019, NYU Center for Experimental Social Science Political Science Conference, 2018
- "Quota Sampling Using Facebook Advertisements": Oxford Internet Institute, 2017, New Faces in Political Methodology Conference, 2017 (Invited)
- "Hands Off My Medicare?: Self-Interest and Conditional Policy Feedback": Centre for Experimental Social Sciences, Nuffield College, University of Oxford, 2017 (Invited), American Political Science Association Annual Meeting, 2016
- "When Will AI Exceed Human Performance? Evidence from AI Experts": Robert Shiller's "Financial Markets" Coursera course salon, 2017 (Invited)
- "Regression Discontinuity Design Using Complex Surveys": Visions in Methodology Conference, 2016 (Invited)
- "Information Equivalence in Survey Experiments": Polmeth Summer Methods Meeting, 2015, NYU Center for Experimental Social Science Political Science Conference, 2015, International Studies Association Annual Conference, 2015, American Political Science Association Annual Meeting, 2014

Professional Experience

Yale Jackson Institute for Global Affairs

Fellow, Kerry Initiative, 2018–2019

Yale School of Forestry & Environmental Studies

Data Scientist, Yale Program on Climate Change Communication, 2015–2018

Pew Research Center Data Lab

Data Lab Fellow, June 2016-August 2016

Yale University Center for Science and Social Science

Data Consultant, 2014-2015

Professional Service

Media Law & Policy Scholars Conference

Co-organizer, 2021–

Paris Peace Forum Working Group on Algorithmic Governance

Member, 2021-

Governance Research in Artificial Intelligence Leadership Network

Member, 2019-

Yale Institution for Social and Policy Studies Experiments Workshop

Coordinator, 2013-2015; 2016-2017

Yale Political Science Methods Skills Enrichment Program

Assistant and Web Developer, 2013-2015

Reviewer for *Political Analysis*, *American Political Science Review*, *American Journal of Political Science*, *Political Science Research and Methods*, *Public Opinion Quarterly*, *Journal of Conflict Resolution*, *AI & Society*, MIT Press, and the ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency.

Additional Training Oxford Internet Institute Summer Doctoral Programme, 2017

University of Oxford

Advanced Quantitative Methods and Research Design, 2013 (funded) Department of Peace and Conflict Research, Uppsala University

SKILLS

Computer: R, Stata, SPSS, Python, ArcGIS, Qualtrics, MTEX, Raspberry Pi

Languages: Chinese (native), French (reading)

REFERENCES

Jacob Hacker: jacob.hacker@yale.edu

Stanley B. Resor Professor, Department of Political Science, Yale University

Allan Dafoe: allandafoe@deepmind.com Senior Staff Research Scientist, DeepMind Founder, Centre for the Governance of AI

Sarah Kreps: sarah.kreps@cornell.edu

John L. Wetherill Professor, Department of Government, Cornell University Adjunct Professor of Law, Cornell Law School

Director, Cornell Tech Policy Lab

Faculty Fellow, Milstein Program in Technology and Humanity at Cornell Tech

Michael C. Horowitz: horom@sas.upenn.edu

Richard Perry Professor, Department of Political Science, University of Pennsylvania Director, Perry World House, University of Pennsylvania

CV updated on January 9, 2022.